A Guide to the Papers of Clarence Day
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Clarence Day 1900-1925
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
7782-c
This collection consists of ca. 92 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was purchased on 1992 June 24.
Scope and Content Information
This collection consists of a letter from Lyon to Day annotated by Lyon, a letter from Louise Godfrey Irwin rejecting a Lyon story, a postal card to Franklin Spier conveying four drawings, the manuscript of "Sonnets in a garden" by Mary Lord, an untitled manuscript on a crescograph by Day, and a photograph of Day.
The remainder of the collection consists of the correspondence of Day protegé Arthur Johnson, a Boston writer whose short stories Day attempted to market. There are letters to Day and Johnson from editors of several magazines, accepting, rejecting and suggesting changes to various stories. With these are two letters from Day to Johnson including one discussing Ibsen and doubting his own ability.
Contents List
- Manuscript
  - "Sonnets in a Garden," three sonnets by Mary Lord n.d., TMsS
    corrected and signed by the author, 1 p.
- Letters
  - Marion [?] to Arthur Johnson. 1900 June 6, ALS
    Johnson's young cousin Marion writes from her family's vacation lodge and wishes him a pleasant vacation, 2 p. on 1 l., w/env.
  - Fanny R. Poole to Arthur Johnson. 1900 Aug 29, ALS
    Copies a poem by Robert Nichols and discusses her choice of poems for an anthology, 8 p. on 2 l., w/env.
  - L.C.M. to Arthur Johnson. 1905 Feb 4, APCS
    Relays praise for a poem Johnson had published in "Poet Lore," 1 p.
  - Harper's Magazine to Clarence Day. 1913 June 30, TL
    Rejects Arthur Johnson's story "The Beauty of It," but likes Johnson's work, 1 p.
  - Wilber L. Cross to Clarence Day 1913 Sep 22, TLS
    Yale Review wants to see several of Johnson's poems. Day passes on the note and suggests to Johnson that he follow up on the suggestion, 1 p.
  - Bellman Magazine to Clarence Day. 1913 Oct 11, TL
    Form letter rejecting a manuscript of Johnson's. Day notes to Johnson that Bellman has missed a good opportunity, 1 p.
  - Atlantic Monthly to Arthur Johnson. 1913 Dec 19, TLS
    Rejects an unnamed short story from Johnson, 1 p.
  - Thomas Wells (of Harper's) to Clarence Day 1913 Dec 24, TLS
    Accepts an unnamed story of Johnson's with a proviso that Johnson improve the plot. Day notes to Johnson that such an unqualified acceptance is a good sign, 2 p. on 1 l.
  - Harper's Editorial Staff to Clarence Day. 1914 Jan 30, TLS
    A formal acceptance of Johnson's story "George's Client," promising payment, 1 p.
  - Lippincott's Magazine to Clarence Day. 1914 Mar 14, TL
    Rejection of Johnson's story "Mrs. Avorr's Clothes," 1 p.
  - Thomas Wells to Clarence Day. 1914 Jun 25, TLS
    Accepts an unnamed story by Johnson subject to some revision, and elimination of "unnecessary vulgarities," 1 p.
  - Thomas Wells to Arthur Johnson 1914 Jun 30, TLS
    Explains his conditions for acceptance of the above unnamed story, 1 p.
  - Thomas Wells to Arthur Johnson 1914 Aug 25, TLS
    In reference to an offensive letter from Johnson, Wells responds by classifying him with "popular" writers rather than great writers. He argues that Harper's knows more about great literature than Johnson, 2 p. on 1 l.
  - Editor of Scribner's to Arthur Johnson. 1914 Sep 3, TLS
    Rejection of Johnson's story "How the Ship Came In," 1 p.
  - Thomas Wells to Arthur Johnson. 1914 Sep 11, TLS
    Wells rejects "How the Ship Came In." Suggests Johnson shorten and tighten it, 1 p.
  - Thomas Wells to Clarence Day. n.d., ALS
    Discusses two of Johnson's stories that he is returning. He suggests sending "Sartorial Romance" to the ladies' magazines, 1 p. portion
  - Julia Tutwiler (of Good Housekeeping) to Arthur Johnson. 1914 Sep 24, TLS
    Good Housekeeping rejects three of Johnson's stories as not suited to their general reader, one of which is "Sartorial Romance," 2 p. on 1 l.
  - William Rose Benet (of Century Magazine) to Arthur Johnson. 1914 Oct 1, TLS
    Benet rejects an unnamed Johnson story, 1 p.
  - Thomas Wells to Arthur Johnson. 1914 Oct 8, TLS
    Suggests that Johnson introduce the "love element" to his story "The Stone Dog" to warm up the young protagonist, 1 p.
  - Thomas Wells to Arthur Johnson. 1914 Oct 15, TLS
    Asks Johnson to prevail upon Mrs. Whitehouse to write an article about her interesting experience with the German Crown-Prince in Berlin, 1 p.
  - Harper's to Arthur Johnson. 1914 Oct 16, TLS
    The editorial staff ask Johnson to clarify the type of machine used in his story "The Dream Drummer" on the proofs, 1 p.
  - Saturday Evening Post to Arthur Johnson. 1914 Oct 19, TLS
    Rejects an unnamed story, 1 p.
  - Thomas Wells to Arthur Johnson. 1914 Oct 27, TLS
    Thanks Johnson for his efforts in the Whitehouse "affair" and for sending him two short stories from another author, Franklin James, 1 p.
  - Thomas Wells to Arthur Johnson. 1914 Oct 30, TLS
    Although Wells sees problems with a story of Johnson's, he has accepted it. He suggests that Johnson add more plot to his stories as Day does, 1 p.
  - Thomas Wells to Arthur Johnson. 1914 Nov 16, TLS
    Offers $150.00 each for two of Johnson's stories. He casts aspersions on most book illustrators, 2 p. on 1 l.
  - Thomas Wells to Arthur Johnson. 1914 Oct 19, TLS
  - Thomas Wells to Arthur Johnson. 1914 Nov 24, TLS
    Finally agrees to another $50.00 for the story, bringing the total to $300.00. Although in theory the magazine pays for quality, Wells admits that better known or established authors command higher fees, 1 p.
  - Harper's to Arthur Johnson. 1914 Dec 3, TLS
    Requests that galley proofs of "My Cousin's Bridegroom" be returned immediately, 1 p.
  - Thomas Wells to Arthur Johnson. 1914 Dec 7, TLS
    Complains of insufficient explanation of a character's actions in an unnamed story and discusses alternatives, 1 p.
  - Thomas Wells to Arthur Johnson. 1914 Dec 8, TLS
    Editorial Considerations, 1 p.
  - Thomas Wells to Arthur Johnson 1914 Dec 22, TLS
    Accuses Johnson of being mercenary and grasping. He suggests that a less irritating and more gracious manner in his letters would serve Johnson better. Johnson minutes to Day that the letter "jarred" him and asks if Day believes the advice, 2 p. on 1 l.
  - Harper's to Arthur Johnson. 1915 Jan 5, TLS
    Rejects Johnson's story "The Story of the Young Berlin Guide," 1 p.
  - Edgar G. Sisson (of Cosmopolitan Magazine to Arthur Johnson. 1915 Jan 26, TLS
    Rejects an unnamed story of Johnson's, 1 p.
  - Thomas Wells to Arthur Johnson. 1915 Jan 28, TLS
    Rejects a story of Johnson's as well as the idea of turning it into a book, but suggests sending it to Century Magazine, 2 p. on 1 l.
  - Churchill Williams (of Saturday Evening Post) to Arthur Johnson. 1915 Jan 26, TLS
  - Robert Bridges (of Scribner's) to Arthur Johnson. 1915 Mar 4, TLS
    Although they want it abridged, Scribner's will purchase "Andy of the Timothy Quartette" for $200.00, 1 p.
  - Scribner's to Arthur Johnson. 1915 Mar 13, TL
    Notice of $200.00 check for the "Timothy" story, 1 p.
  - Robert Bridges to Arthur Johnson. 1915 Mar 15, TLS
    Scribner's sends the proofs of "Timothy" and asks Johnson to shorten it, 1 p.
  - Robert Bridges to Arthur Johnson 1915 Mar 17, TLS
    Bridges rejects an unnamed story that Johnson had re-submitted, 1 p.
  - Sue Goree to Arthur Johnson 1915 Apr 5, TLS
    Writes to scold Johnson for exaggerating the Texas dialect in his story "My Cousin's Bridegroom," and provides corrections, 3 p. on 1 l.
  - Robert Bridges to Arthur Johnson 1915 Apr 20, ALS
    Rejects Johnson's story "Mr. Eberdeen's House," 1 p.
  - William Rose Benet to Arthur Johnson 1915 Apr 20, ALS
    Cryptic response that Century does want an unnamed story by September, 1 p.
  - Douglas Doty (of Century) to Arthur Johnson 1915 Jun 9, TLS
    Advises Johnson that Century has accepted "Mr. Eberdeen's House," and will purchase it for $100.00, 1 p.
  - Edgar Sisson to Arthur Johnson 1915 Jun 11, TLS
    Cosmopolitan rejects Johnson's story "The One Hundred Eightieth Meridian," 1 p.
  - Douglas Doty to Arthur Johnson 1915 Jun 15, TLS
    In response to a complaint by Johnson, Doty offers $200.00 for "Mr. Eberdeen's House." Johnson notes to Day that Day may answer for him, 1 p.
  - Douglas Doty to Arthur Johnson. 1915 Jun 29, TLS
    Explains that each story is priced according to its own merits and the offer of $200.00 won't set a poor precedent, 1 p.
  - Century to Arthur Johnson. 1915 Jun 29, TL
    Request to please return the proofs by July 3, 1 p.
  - William Rose Benet to Arthur Johnson 1915 Aug 23, TL
    Century likes an unnamed story of Johnson's but wants the obvious character analysis cut out, 1 p.
  - Carl Hovey (of Metropolitan Magazine) to Arthur Johnson. 1915 Oct 12, TLS
    Asks Johnson to re-work "The Devil's Joke-Box" by the end of the month, and exchanges news of mutual friends, 1 p.
  - Carl Hovey to Arthur Johnson 1915 Nov 1, TLS
    Anxious to see the revised version of "The Devil's Joke-Box," 1 p.
  - Thomas Wells to Arthur Johnson. 1915 Nov 29, TLS
    Asks Johnson for a very free hand to edit an unnamed story of Johnson's, and requests stories with more "humor and youth" in them, 1 p.
  - William Rose Benet to Arthur Johnson. 1915 Dec 6, TLS
    Century rejects an unidentified story of Johnson's that Benet personally liked, 1 p.
  - Thomas Wells to Arthur Johnson. 1915 Dec 27, TLS
    Rejects "The Beauty of It" for a second time; not sufficiently interesting, 1 p.
  - George Wheelock, treasurer of the Century Co. Publishers, to Arthur Johnson. 1916 Jan 26, TLS
    Advises Johnson that he is free to sell the right to reprint his story; it is called "second serial right," 1 p.
  - Robert Bridges to Arthur Johnson. 1916 Feb 9, TLS
    Although Bridges rejects Johnson's story "The Rules," he states that he enjoys Johnson's stories but finds them too long for Scribner's Magazine, 1 p.
  - Thomas Wells to Arthur Johnson. 1916 Mar 8, TLS
    Rejects an unnamed story of Johnson's although he likes its psychology; he suggests Johnson try Scribner's, 1 p.
  - Atlantic Monthly to Arthur Johnson 1916 Mar 17, TLS
  - Edgar Sisson to Arthur Johnson 1916 Mar 22, ALS
    Thanks Johnson for showing him an unnamed story whose "probing analysis" is very effective, 1 p.
  - Robert Bridges to Arthur Johnson 1916 Mar 28, TLS
    Rejects the revised version of "A Sartorial Romance," having already rejected the original, 1 p.
  - Thomas Wells to Arthur Johnson. 1916 Apr 14, TLS
    Rejects a revised story, but asks for new stories, 1 p.
  - Thomas Wells to Arthur Johnson. 1916 Aug 16, TLS
    Rejects a story and suggests that Johnson has wandered from his own field into New England regionalism, which other writers do better, 1 p.
  - Carl Hovey to Arthur Johnson. 1916 Sep 21, TLS
    Asks Johnson to send the "detective" story right away and mentions mutual friends, 1 p.
  - Carl Hovey to Arthur Johnson 1916 Dec 14, TLS
    Comments on an unnamed story that may yet need some revision. He extends an invitation to a banquet given by Metropolitan Magazine on December 22. They are inviting such authors as deserve "food and booze at the hands of the old Metropolitan." Day will be attending, 1 p.
  - Reine Stanton 1917 Feb 5, TLS
    Writes to compliment Johnson on his story "The Devil's Joke-Box" published in the December issue of Writes to compliment Johnson on his story "The Devil's Joke-Box" published in the December issue of Metropolitan, 1 p.
  - Robert Bridges to Arthur Johnson. 1917 Feb 5, TLS
    Acknowledges receipt of Johnson's short novel and promises special attention for it, 1 p.
  - Robert Bridges to Arthur Johnson. 1917 Feb 27, TLS
    Highly praises "Mortimer," a story of Johnson's, but its length precludes publication. Bridges suggests he make cuts throughout the story, 1 p.
  - Thomas Wells to Arthur Johnson. 1917 Mar 21, TLS
    Rejects an unnamed story because its theme is inappropriate to a popular magazine, 1 p.
  - Robert Bridges to Arthur Johnson. 1917 Apr 9, TLS
    Approves of the way Johnson has "boiled down" "Mortimer" and accepts it for publication. He argues with Johnson over a plot detail-the length of time it takes to travel from New York to Peoria by rail, 1 p.
  - Scribner's to Arthur Johnson. 1917 May 3, TL
    Note with check for $200.00 for "Mortimer," 1 p.
  - Atlantic Monthly to Arthur Johnson. 1917 Aug 17, TLS
    Atlantic's editors believe Johnson has a gift for the eerie, and his story shows skill and cleverness, but they reject it, 1 p.
  - Thomas Wells to Arthur Johnson. 1917 Oct 9, TLS
    Compliments Johnson on an unnamed story, and subject to some revision, he accepts it, 2 p. on 1 l.
  - Thomas Wells to Arthur Johnson. 1918 Feb 14, TLS
    Relays a comment on Johnson's work from William Dean Howells and rejects a new story, "His Mortal Coil" for the over-sophistication of Johnson's method which makes the story unreal to Wells. He notes that Johnson has received $350.00 each for his last two stories, 2 p. on 1 l.
  - Herbert C[?] (of New Republic) to Arthur Johnson. 1918 Mar 8, TLS
    The New Republic acccepts an article by Johnson on Herman Melville and Henry James provided he makes several revisions, 1 p.
  - Herbert C[?] to Arthur Johnson. 1918 Mar 27, TLS
    The New Republic accepts the Melville-James article and will pay at their usual rate of two cents per word, 1 p.
  - Lee Foster Hartman (of Harper's) to Arthur Johnson. 1918 May 3, TLS
    Rejects the story "The Two Lovers," relates that Wells has left to do Red Cross work in France, and asks that since he shares Wells' interest in Johnson's work, Johnson should send his stories directly to him, 1 p.
  - Francis McCrudden to Mr. Shaw. 1918 Jun 12, ALS
    Discusses the publication of Shaw's book on the Peterborough School, 2 p. on 1 l.
  - Lee Foster Hartman to Arthur Johnson. 1918 Aug 9, TLS
    Accepts Johnson's story "A Flight from the Fireside" provided some dialogue is revised and made less sentimental, 1 p.
  - Thomas Wells to Arthur Johnson. 1919 Mar 31, TLS
    Announces that he has returned to the United States and asks for a story, as Harper's is running short of fiction, 1 p.
  - New Republic to Arthur Johnson. 1919 Aug 26, TL
    Check enclosure for $40.00 for the Melville-James article, 1 p.
  - Thomas Wells to Arthur Johnson. 1919 Oct 14, TLS
    Reports Harper's terms for publishing Johnson's book of short stories. He admits that they do not expect to make a profit but are doing this as a goodwill gesture to keep Johnson in Harper's"corner," 2 p. on 1 l.
  - Ferris Greenslet (of Houghton Mifflin Co.) to Carl Hovey 1919 Oct 20, TLS
    Greenslet and fellow editor R.L. Straife are impressed with Johnson's stories but find some of them "rather long for their substance." He suggests that Johnson publish a novel before he publishes a volume of stories. This, he claims, is a typical method "in the trade" of boosting sales, 2 p. on 1 l.
  - William Briggs (of Harper's) to Arthur Johnson. 1920 Apr 26, TLS
    Under the Rose is scheduled for an early autumn publication so it will fit into the "fall fiction handicap." Barring labor problems they hope for an October 1 date, 1 p.
  - A.W. Rushmore to Arthur Johnson 1920 Jun 14, TLS
    Rushmore of Harper's manufacturing department, offers a counter-suggestion to Johnson's choice of cloth color for his book cover. Nevertheless, he stresses that Johnson has the final choice, 1 p.
  - Thomas Wells to Arthur Johson. 1920 Oct 6, TLS
    The cost of the plates exceeds the amount previously quoted. Wells suggests that Johnson may pay the difference in good short stories if he chooses. Wells also sends Johnson a second set of author's copies since the first set had not arrived, 1 p.
  - Clarence Day to Arthur Johnson. n.d., ALS
    Day discusses Ibsen's expertise in plot construction. He likens himself to a proprietor of a literary oyster bed and uses the pearl seeking operation as a metaphor for the literary profession. He bewails his discontent and despair over his financial and critical lack of success. He compliments Johnson on his ability but asserts that he (Day) is in the wrong field, 5 p. w/ illustrations.
  - Clarence Day to Arthur Johnson. [1920], ALS
    Day responds to Johnson's announcement that he will dedicate Under the Rose to him by musing that he has been a bad influence on Johnson, concentrating his advice on monetary rather than literary issues. He discusses a new idea that due to problems in transport and delivery, magazines have become "perishable goods," 2 p. w/ illustrations.
  - Elizabeth Shurtliff to Arthur Johnson. 1923 Oct 29, ALS
    Discusses the placement of several of Johnson's poems and stories and their illustrations in some monthly anthologies, 3 p. on 1 l.
  - Hal R[?] to Arthur Johnson. n.y. Oct 15, ALS
    Writes to say that the choir-boy story which he had from Clarence Day is the best he has seen of Johnson's work. He plans to be in Boston in business and will see Johnson then, 3 p. on 1 l.
  - Hal R[?] to Arthur Johnson. n.d., ALS
    Likes Johnson's story on "Charley," and thinks its "oddness" makes it a better story, 1 p.
  - Portion of Letter to Arthur Johnson. n.d., ALS
    Some friend of Johnson's, temporarily based in Mexico describes the setting using several literary allusions, 2 p. on 1 l.
- Photographs
  - Matted sepia photo of Clarence Day seated in an old open car, possibly a "Model T," apparently in the countryside. n.d., sepia photo